<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arraignment of Iohn van Olden Barneuelt late Aduocate of Holland and West-Freisland Containing the articles alleadged against him, and the reasons of his execution, being performed vpon the 13. of May anno 1619. stilo nouo, in the inner court of the Grauen Hage in Holland. Together with a letter written by the Generall States, vnto the particular Vnited Prouinces, concerning the foresaid action. Published by authoritie, and with priuiledge of the States Generall.</title>
            <author>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113450</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848684</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848684</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 930:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arraignment of Iohn van Olden Barneuelt late Aduocate of Holland and West-Freisland Containing the articles alleadged against him, and the reasons of his execution, being performed vpon the 13. of May anno 1619. stilo nouo, in the inner court of the Grauen Hage in Holland. Together with a letter written by the Generall States, vnto the particular Vnited Prouinces, concerning the foresaid action. Published by authoritie, and with priuiledge of the States Generall.</title>
                  <author>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Ralph Rounthwait at the signe of the Golden Lion in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes "A proclamation made by the Generall States of the vnited Netherland Prouinces, for the holding of a generall fast".</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:1"/>
            <p>THE ARRAIGNMENT Of <hi>John van Olden Barneuelt</hi> late Aduocate of HOLLAND and WEST-FREISLAND.</p>
            <p>Containing the Articles alleadged againſt him, and the reaſons of his execution, being performed vpon the 13. of May <hi>Anno</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo Nouo,</hi> In the inner Court of the <hi>Grauen Hage</hi> in HOLLAND.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH A LETTER written by the <hi>Generall States,</hi> vnto the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Vnited Prouinces,</hi> concerning the foreſaid action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authoritie, and with priuiledge of the States Generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Ralph Rounthwait</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Golden Lion</hi> in Pauls Church-yard. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:2"/>
            <head>THE PRIVILEDGE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE States generall of the vnited NETHERLANDS, haue giuen and granted licence vnto <hi>Hillebrant Jacobſon,</hi> ſworne Printer to them, and to the States of <hi>Holland</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and by theſe preſents giue and grant licence, that he onely for the ſpace of two yeares, next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the date hereof, ſhall print and deliuer out in Dutch, the ſentence and iudgement giuen &amp; pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Iudges, by them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto appointed, vpon and againſt <hi>Iohn van Olden Barnevelt,</hi> ſometime Aduocate or Counſellor of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Freſeland,</hi> and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted on his perſon, vpon the 13 of May 1619. <hi>Stilo novo,</hi> in the inner Court of the Hage, for bidding
<pb facs="tcp:13795:3"/>
and prohibiting all other Printers, and ſubiects of theſe Prouinces, to print, or cauſe the aforeſaid Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence within the time aforeſaid of two yeares to bee printed or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out in Dutch, vpon paine of forfeiture of ſuch Bookes, and further of the ſumme of 300 <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollus Guldens:</hi> the one third part thereof to the behoofe of him that ſhall be the officer to execute the Commiſsion: an other third part, to the vſe of the poore, and the laſt third part to the vſe. &amp; benefit of the aforeſaid <hi>Hillebrant Jacobſon,</hi> giuen in the Aſſembly of the ſaid Generall States in <hi>Grauen-Hage,</hi> the 14 of May 1619. I. V. Dorth. v<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By order from the generall States.</hi> C. AERSEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:3"/>
            <head>THE COPIE OF A LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, written by the generall States, vnto the particular vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Netherlands.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſend your Honors herewith, a copie of the ſentence, which the Iudges thereunto appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, pronounced against the priſoners (long deliberated vpon by vs) which on the 13 of this preſent moneth, was publiſhed, and execution done vpon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Iohn van Olden Barnevelt,</hi> late Counſellor or Aduocate of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>VVeſt-Freſeland:</hi> The ſaid Iudges withall ſent vs certaine ouertures, of diuers other points, that were made knowne vnto them, and are not mentioned in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſentence, which according to the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, &amp; conſequences therof, gaue great ſuſpition that he had intelligence with the enemy, and wholy bended his actions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſeeking neuertheleſſe not to giue nor
<pb facs="tcp:13795:4"/>
miniſter any offence to the other ſide, but to the contrary made ſhew to fauour the ſame; but for that the ſubſtance of the confeſsions made vpon thoſe points, were ſuch, that no definitiue ſentence could haue bin giuen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, without further inquiſition, and ſharper examination, which by the ſaid Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, was not thought conuenient, in reſpect of his great age, and other conſiderations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeruice of the Land, as alſo for that the deciſion of them &amp; other matters, could no longer be delayed, and that the articles in the ſaid ſentence contained, are ſufficient to condemne him; we haue omitted them, and thought it good and neceſſarie hereby to certifie you thereof, beſeeching God to haue your Honors &amp; vs in his holy keeping: from the Hage the 19. of May 1619. vnderwritten</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iohn van Dorth v<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
                  </hi> and a litle lower, <hi>By the order of the States, C. AERSEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="judgment">
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:4"/>
            <head>THE IVDGMENT GIVEN AND PRONOVNCED vpon <hi>John van Olden Barneuelt,</hi> late Aduocate of HOLLAND and WEST-FRESELAND, together with his execution performed vpon the 13 of May 1619. <hi>Stylo novo.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>IOhn van Olden Barnevelt</hi> ſometime Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate or Counſellor of the Prouinces of Holland and Weſt-Freeſland, and at this preſent committed to priſon, Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners being by the generall States ordained and appointed to examine him, and to make
<pb facs="tcp:13795:5"/>
report thereof vnto the Iudges by the ſaid generall States ordained to ſit vpon the ſame, without racke or any torment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, (as to the ſaid Iudges alſo it manifeſtly appeared)</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>1</head>
               <p>That notwithſtanding, it is not lawfull for any man, to breake or violate the vnitie, and fundamentall lawes, whereupon the gouernment of the vnited Netherlands is grounded, and whereby the ſaid Countries (by Gods ſpeciall bleſſing, notwithſtanding all the forces, practiſes and deuices of their enemies and euill willers) hath bin hitherto preſerued and defended: he the ſaid priſoner had taken vpon him, to trouble the ſtate of the Religion, and thereby to bring the Church of God into great trouble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie. To that end had maintained and put in practiſe, moſt exorbitant and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maximes againſt the ſtate of the Land, and among them, with great boldnes, of himſelfe and by his complices inſerted, that
<pb facs="tcp:13795:5"/>
ſome of the Prouinces of the ſaid vnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, had power &amp; authoritie of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to order and diſpoſe of religion at their wills and pleaſures, and that the reſt of the Prouinces had nothing to doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>2</head>
               <p>That without commiſſion or authoritie, he had in his owne houſe made certaine proteſtations in the name of the Prouinces of Holland, Vtrecht, and Oueriſſell, whereby they togither, by manner of complot (againſt all order vſed in the aſſemblies of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall States) proteſted, that the Deputies of the Prouinces which were appointed for the furthering of the Nationall Synode, would be the authors and cauſers of great troubles and inconueniences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>That he contemning the good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſels of diuers Princes, Lords, and
<pb facs="tcp:13795:6"/>
noble Perſonages both in and without the land, as much as in him lay, had ſought to withſtand and hinder the remedies procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the ceaſing of controuerſie in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>That to further and maintaine his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes aforeſaid, he had abuſed certaine of the mightieſt Potentates with vnſeemely and ſiniſter practiſes, and to that end by his owne authoritie inſtructed, and cauſed to be inſtructed, the Ambaſſadors for the States with vntrue propoſitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>That he alſo had taken vpon him to write to the States Ambaſſador reſident in Great Britannie, that if any thing ſhould be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſaid King concerning the ſtate of Religion, that it ſhould be ſent to the States of Holland; and that he ſhould procure the ſtaying thereof, vntill he had ſent the copie
<pb facs="tcp:13795:6"/>
vnto him to conſider of it, and to ſtay his anſwer thereupon, before he ſent the ſame, and that the letters ſhould be directed vnto him, that he might deliuer them, for the good and ſeruice of the land (aſſuming to himſelfe all the authoritie and gouernment thereof.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>That he tooke vpon him, in the name of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frieſland,</hi> to write to the King of <hi>France,</hi> that thoſe States Generall that proclaimed a nationall Synod, vſurped the names of the Generall States, wiſhing his Maieſtie not to ſend any of his ſubiects vnto the ſaid Synod, but rather to aid and aſſiſt thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> againſt the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the States.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>That by indirect meanes he had ſought for and procured letters from the King of <hi>England,</hi> which he himſelfe had firſt drawne
<pb facs="tcp:13795:7"/>
and corrected, and then ſent them ouer to the Ambaſſador, tending to the furthering of his owne deſignes, which he himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the generall States, but made them not acquainted in what manner he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured them, writing to the ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that he ſhould not by any means make the Ambaſſadors at that time in <hi>England</hi> for the generall States, acquainted therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>8.</head>
               <p>That for the better furtherance of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and pretences, by the ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors meanes he ſought to procure the like letters againe from the King of <hi>England,</hi> which when he could not get, he did not ſticke to preſume to tax the ſaid King, with being the cauſe of the troubles that were then riſen in the vnited Prouinces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>That, to procure the more and greater trouble in religion, hee had placed and
<pb facs="tcp:13795:7"/>
brought into the Churches diuers hereticall Diuines and Teachers, and in the mannage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the State had put in ſuch men, as he thought to be fit inſtruments for the effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and furtherance of his faction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>That he likewiſe had brought to paſſe, that his ſaid creatures and inſtruments at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſeuerall times, and ſundry places, contrary to all good order of gouernment, had holden diuers conuenticles and ſecret aſſemblies, where, by him and his complices it was determined how they might proceed in their bad pretence: and to the end the ſame might be authorized vnder the names of the States of Holland and Weſt-Freiſland, he had ſo plotted, that by multitude of voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (contrary to the will and deſire of ſome of the chiefeſt members of Holland) they might reſolue vpon that which they deſired and intended: and yet he himſelfe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that ſuch priuate aſſemblies are not to be permitted in a well-gouerned Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:8"/>
               <head>11</head>
               <p>That he did not ſeeke to hinder the rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous commiſſions in ſome places ſent forth againſt the true profeſſors of religion, whereby they were vpon ſtrict penalties forbidden the exerciſe of the true religion, making them hatefull in all places both within and without the Land, by the names of ſtrangers, and Puritans, who there Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deriſing, cauſed the ſubiects to contend with their Gouernors. Notwithſtanding that all the vnited Prouinces together, by many and ſundry treaties, agreements, and reſolutions, (whereof he himſelfe, as one of the States, had beene the author and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) had promiſed and bound themſelues one vnto another, with body, life, and goods, to maintaine, preſerue and vphold, the reformed euangelicall religion, receiued and preached in euery place of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, without any alteration thereof what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. And that for confirmation thereof, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1588. the oathes of all the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,
<pb facs="tcp:13795:8"/>
Generals, Captaines, and ſouldiers, in one point ſpecially mentioned the ſame, which was that they ſhould ſweare to bee true and faithfull to the generall States, who by the vnitie and faithfull combination of promiſe, ſhould vphold and maintaine the true reformed religion: and that in all the treaties and compoſitions made with ſuch townes as they either won, or that yeelded themſelues to them, one ſpeciall Article was, that they ſhould yeeld to the preaching of the aforeſaid religion, which by all their adherents and allies had beene receiued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, and accepted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>That he eſteeming all this not to be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to effect his bad and erroneous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, ſought by the meanes of his compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and adherents, to perturbe and trouble the politique State, deuiſing to inuent and finde the meanes to reduce and bring the gouernment thereof into diſorder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, by meanes thereof the better to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:13795:9"/>
his miſchieuous pretence againſt the ſecuritie and proſperitie of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>13</head>
               <p>That to the ſame end, and for a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faction, vnder diuers ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, hee had kindled the fire of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and procured all manner of diſtruſts betweene the Prouinces, and making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe head of the faction, had cauſed the Deputies of eight townes in Holland to hold diuers ſecret aſſemblies, vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine points by them agreed vpon, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the reſt of the townes, (and ſo by plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of voices, hauing formerly complot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together) in the aſſemblie of the States of Holland, to bring them in, and to make ſuch reſolutions thereupon as they had formerly determined. In which priuate aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, the Deputies of the ſaid eight townes, among other things, firſt complot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and agreed vpon diuers points, (which at ſeuerall times were by them debated) and concluded to bring to effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:9"/>
               <head>14</head>
               <p>That he himſelfe had therein inſerted the ſharpe and ſeuere reſolution made the 18. of Auguſt 1617. and againſt the wills and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of diuers chiefe members of the ſaid aſſemblie, cauſed the ſame to be ratified and confirmed. By which reſolution, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions of ordinary Iuſtice made againſt their pretences, were declared and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be void and of none effect: and the Magiſtrates of the townes, warranted, not to obey the ſame; and ſuch as were thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to incited and conſenting, authoriſed and allowed, of their owne authorities, for their defences, to raiſe new companies of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to giue them another oath (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to their oath of allegeance made to the States Generall) by the which alſo all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Iuſtices, and thoſe that were by oath bound vnto the particular Prouinces of Holland and Weſt-Freiſland, were ſworne to maintaine and further the ſaid reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And further ordained, that all Generals, Captaines and ſouldiers of the ordinary
<pb facs="tcp:13795:10"/>
companies, ſhould earneſtly be charged and commanded, vpon paine of loſing of their places, to be obedient to the States, their pay-maſters, and the Magiſtrates of the townes where they lay in garriſon, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any other prohibition or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement made to the contrary: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it followed, that diuers townes in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (whereof ſome before that by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and counſell had begunne to take vp ſouldiers) vpon the ſame reſolution (and his ſecret inſtigation that they ſhould looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues and their ſecurities) began to raiſe a great number of ſouldiers, giuing them a particular oath, as aforeſaid, with ſpeciall charge to be obedient only to their commandements, againſt all men whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, and particularly againſt the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and his Excellencie, in ſuch caſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid townes (ſo ſtrengthning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with new ſouldiers) ſhould iudge and vnderſtand the proceedings of the ſaid generalitie and his Excellencie to tend vnto the ouerthrow of their particular rights and priuiledges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:10"/>
               <head>15</head>
               <p>That he by force of the ſaid reſolution, was a meanes to procure Commiſſioners to be ſent vnto the Brill, who (without the knowledge of his Excellencie being State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder and Captaine generall) going thither, cauſed the ordinary garriſons therein to take their oathes in manner aforeſaid, and ſuch as would not, were threatned to bee caſhierd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>That he, within few dayes after the ſaid reſolution was made, went to Vtrecht, and counſelled ſome of the States there likewiſe, to raiſe new companies of ſouldiers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the accuſtomed manner, and the common oath of the generalitie and his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, as Captaine generall, which they accordingly raiſed, with a particular oath as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:11"/>
               <head>17</head>
               <p>And when the Generall States, perceiuing the ſaid raiſing of ſouldiers to be contrary to order and generall cuſtome, thought it fit to aduertiſe them by letter, to ſurceaſe from the ſame, that he was the author and cauſe, that the ſaid States of Vtrecht, tooke vpon them by letters of the 5. of September 1617. to excuſe their ſaid proceeding vnto the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall States, with vaine and idle pretences, as that they were raiſed for the diuerting of popular commotion, and yet he knew well, that the defence and preſeruation of the Prouinces, townes, and forts thereof, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, by the vnion is referred to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the generalitie of our vnited States in generall: as alſo, that by the counſell of State holden in Vtrecht <hi>anno</hi> 1610. it was likewiſe ordered, that whatſoeuer belonged vnto the ſecuritie, peace and tranquilitie of the towne and territories of Vtrecht in all reſpects ſhould be referred to the ſaid States Generall. And that then a great garriſon,
<pb facs="tcp:13795:11"/>
belonging vnto the ſaid Generall States, lay therein, which while the Armies were in Gelders and Cleaueland, was not dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: And beſides, that by the ſaid States, it was expreſly ordered, not to diminiſh the ſaid garriſon, but rather (if it were found neceſſary) to increaſe the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>18</head>
               <p>That by the conſent and knowledge of him, this inſtruction was inſerted, and the new ſouldiers were raiſed in Vtrecht, by the which, cleane contrary to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations and reaſons in the letter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid pretended, the ſaid new ſouldiers were bound, to ſerue both without and within the ſaid Prouince, againſt all and euery perſon, both by water and by land, onely vnder the commandement or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the ſtates of Vtrecht, and that they ſhould not onely be ready at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the ſaid States of Vtrecht, but alſo aide and aſſiſt their good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, frends, and allies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>19</head>
               <p>And as in Vtrecht newes was brought
<pb facs="tcp:13795:12"/>
that his Excellencie the Prince of Orange, was to come into, and paſſe through the ſaid towne, a letter was by the ſaid States of Vtrecht (not without the ſaid priſoners knowledge, as then being in Vtrecht) ſent vnto the ſaid Prince, to deſire him, not to paſſe, nor come through that towne, with earneſt aduice to follow their counſel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: he not many dayes before, aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the Secretarie <hi>Ledenberch</hi> by priuate let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that it was fit and expedient for them, to keepe a ſtrong watch at their gates, and alſo that both from aboue and beneath the riuer of <hi>Leck,</hi> they ſhould be aduertiſed by the next townes, whether any ſouldiers were comming vp or downe the ſaid riuer, as alſo that the like was to be done vpon the way that entred into the towne by Amersfort gate, deſiring <hi>Ledenberch</hi> when he had read the letters to burne them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>20</head>
               <p>That he, by his inſtructions and counſels brought to paſſe, that by the Deputies of the
<pb facs="tcp:13795:12"/>
aforeſaid eight townes, firſt in priuate mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, in vnaccuſtomed places, and vndue times, a certaine procuration, or an act of vnion, was drawne, which afterward alſo, was in ſome of the ſaid townes by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the <hi>Common Councell,</hi> and in ſome of them without their knowledge, concluded and agreed vpon, the 14. of May 1618. whereby they authorized their Deputies, to conſult, aduiſe and reſolue with the States and Deputies of the other townes, vpon a meanes of preſent reſiſtance; as alſo, all togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to prouide for, and to aſſure, all ſuch promiſes of aſſiſtance, helpe, and indemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as they ſhould finde to be neceſſarie, needfull and conuenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>21</head>
               <p>That he cauſed a copie of the ſame act to be giuen vnto <hi>Monſ: Modesberghen</hi> by <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gherbet</hi> the pentionarie, and withall deſired him to conſider thereof, who thereupon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently went to Vtrecht, and procured the like act there alſo to be propounded, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning
<pb facs="tcp:13795:13"/>
likewiſe an authoritie to bee giuen vnto their Deputies touching the two former points of ſtricter vnion, and certaine and preſent meanes of reſiſtance: and for that the towne, togither with ſome other of the members of the States, would not grant nor conſent thereunto, he deſired the Borghomaſter <hi>van Pol</hi> (then being in the Hage) by his letters to moue them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, or purpoſely to goe thither about it: which to effect, the ſaid Borghomaſter went perſonally thither; but the Magiſtrate of Vtrecht perceiuing whereunto the force of the ſaid procuration or authoritie tended, would not conſent thereunto, but with an expreſſe limitation, that the Committies, ſhould not extend their authoritie to the furtherance or procuring of preſent or new extremities, or to the making of new vnitie with any ſeuerall Prouinces, townes or members thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>22</head>
               <p>That when the States of Vtrecht, to eaſe
<pb facs="tcp:13795:13"/>
themſelues of the burthen and charge of maintayning the new companies of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and to let and withſtand the decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their treaſure and reuenues, vpon the 19. of Iune 1618. <hi>Stilo vet:</hi> found it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to ſend a competent number of their Deputies to the Hage, togither with <hi>Monſieur Modesberghen</hi> and others, at the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Generall States, to be holden there, and with his Excellencie the Prince of Orange, as Gouernor and Captaine Generall of the Prouince of Vtrecht, to agree vpon the diſcharging of the ſaid new ſouldiers, he counſelled <hi>Ledenbergh</hi> (as then one of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties) in his owne houſe (hauing intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their ſaid commiſſion by the ſaid <hi>Ledenbergh)</hi> not to diſcouer the ſame vnto the Prince of Orange, but to keepe it ſecret, and to follow other aduice by him giuen vnto the ſaid <hi>Ledenbergh;</hi> not remembring that he himſelfe confeſſeth that he knew full well, the great charge and burthen of the Land, and the vnfitnes thereof for the maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of new companies of ſouldiers, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo great a number.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:14"/>
               <head>23</head>
               <p>That he had intelligence giuen him, that the ſaid <hi>Ledenbergh,</hi> togither with the pentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <hi>Hoogherbet,</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Iohn Vtenbogaet</hi> did conſult vpon the reaſons, and motiues, that ſhould be obſerued with the aforeſaid Deputie of the States of V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht, to diuert, and diſſwade them not to put their commiſſion in effect; as alſo, that the ſame deliberation holden, and required by <hi>Ledenbergh,</hi> ſhould be kept ſecret: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followed that the ſaid <hi>Hoogerbets</hi> and his complices, in the houſe of <hi>Daniel Treſel</hi> Clarke to the generall Sates, meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with many very ſharpe and pernicious ſpeeches, and motions vſed by <hi>Grotius,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Deputies of Vtrecht to ſhew their authoritie; whereof alſo the ſaid pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner was aduertiſed, and whereby alſo the ſaid Deputies were compelled to goe backe againe to Vtrecht, without ſhewing their commiſſion, notwithſtanding, that by the States of Vtrecht, they were reiteratiuely willed and required to doe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:14"/>
               <head>24</head>
               <p>That he earneſtly aduiſed the ſaid Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at their departure, to ſtand againſt the aſſembly of a Nationall Synode, and to vrge the continuance of their new companies of ſouldiers, as alſo, to keepe good and ſtrong watch both at their gates and in their townes, adding thereunto, that if it fell out, that at the firſt the buſineſſe were not found out, and that the ſaid new ſouldiers ſhould thereby, be longer held in pay, that then they ſhould haue cauſe togither with the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed townes in Holland to enter into fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther communication, vpon the increaſing, and aſſuring of the number of the new ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which they togither ſhould thinke fit for their neceſſarie aſſurance, and to finde out meanes for the maintenance of them, by reciprocall aſſiſtance among them: he alſo aduertiſed diuers Deputies of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid eight townes thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <head>25</head>
               <p>That he alſo perſwaded the towne of
<pb facs="tcp:13795:15"/>
Schonehouen, beſides the ordinary and common contributions by them to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed for the neceſſarie defence of the land, and payment of the garriſons, to agree vnto the raiſing and payment of the new compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies then raiſed. And alſo that he thought it conuenient, and winked thereat, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers townes (to the eminent danger of the land) gaue their conſents with ſtrange and vnaccuſtomed exceptions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>26</head>
               <p>That to make the ſeruice and counſell of his Excellencie in all places vnprofitable and of no force, he ſought to diſgrace and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize his ſaid Excellencie by diuers calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations, and vtterly to diſhonour him, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king men beleeue that hee ſought to haue the ſoueraigntie of the Land in his owne power, and that he had practiſed the ſame by premeditated counſell, at the very ſame time and houre, that the neceſſitie of the Common-wealth (in the higheſt degree) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired his ſaid Excellencies aduice, in ſecret
<pb facs="tcp:13795:15"/>
aſſemblies of certaine Deputies for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, being his confederates: with other ſuch like imputations; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he alſo had conference with other Countries, by letters written in ciphers, and by him ſent abroad.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>27</head>
               <p>That he by certaine perſons expreſly ſent out in the night time, aduertiſed the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of Leyden, that his Excellencie was to goe from the Hage, and that apparantly he would goe thither, that they therfore ſhould ſtand vpon their guard, and aduertiſe other their neighbour townes thereof, that they alſo ſhould looke vnto themſelues. Vpon which his aduice it followed, that the watch-bell being rung, the new ſouldiers and ſhot ran to armes at midnight, and ſome townes in Holland by them were aduertiſed with all ſpeed to looke vnto themſelues as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: as alſo that the gates of the ſaid towne were kept ſhut the next day after, vntill hee gaue them other aduice, that his Excellencie
<pb facs="tcp:13795:16"/>
was gone another way; although he had no intent of harme againſt that, nor any other towne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <head>28</head>
               <p>That hee confeſſed, that hee was much grieued and diſcontented, when he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the towne of Brill, to preuent the ſending of new companies of ſouldiers thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was guarded by the ordinary garriſon of the Generall States, therein placed by his Excellencie, and that he wrought from Vtrecht to the ordinary counſels of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Weſt-Freiſland, to aduertiſe and forewarne all the townes of the ſaid Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to looke well vnto themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="article">
               <head>29</head>
               <p>That alſo to withdraw the ordinary ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers from the obedience of the Generall States and of his Excellencie, he had labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all the meanes he could to make them to vnderſtand, that they were by oath
<pb facs="tcp:13795:16"/>
bound, before all others to obey the States of the particular Prouinces, (their pay-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) though it were againſt the generall States and his Excellencie; as alſo that they ought and were bound expreſly to reſiſt their commandements, whenſoeuer they ſhould vndertake any thing contrary to the wills or reſolutions of the States of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, and the Magiſtrates of the townes wherein they ſhould lie in garriſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="article">
               <head>30</head>
               <p>And when the Generall States, perceiuing that they could not by any ſerious aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements or inſtances attaine to the diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the new companies of ſouldiers, thought it conuenient to ſend other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitties with his Excellencie to Vtrecht, he practiſed and found meanes, that by very few Gentlemen, three townes, and ſome counſell of State, which had no commiſſion ſo to doe, <hi>Hoogerbeets, Grotius,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were appointed Committies to goe to Vtrecht, and there in the name of the States
<pb facs="tcp:13795:17"/>
of Holland and Weſt-Freeſland, to profer all aide and counſell to the States and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of Vtrecht, for the ſtaying and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the diſcharge of the new companies, giuing letters alſo to the commanders of the ſouldiers there, that were likely to be diſcharged, (drawne by him the ſaid priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) and yet not read in the aſſembly then holden; whereby they were aduertiſed that they were bound and obliged, to be true and obedient to their pay-maſters, togither with the States of the reſpectiue Prouinces, wherein they lay in garriſon, or were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe imployed: and to aide and aſſiſt them in vpholding of all their reſolutions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing or attempting any thing, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to be done or attempted to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="article">
               <head>31</head>
               <p>That he alſo affirmed, that the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion giuen to his Excellencie, and other their Committies of the Generall States, touching the diſcharging of the new Companies, if it
<pb facs="tcp:13795:17"/>
were done without the conſent of the States of Vtrecht, was contrary to the vnion, and would be a cauſe of force which might be vſed to expell force, as well as they did and were compelled to doe againſt the King of Spaine and his Gouernors; whereas he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his remonſtrances giuen out in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſheweth, that all violent courſes are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſiue and ruinous for the ſtate of the Land, and a right Spaniſh counſell, tending to the ſubuerſion and vtter ruine of theſe famous Prouinces. Whereupon it followed, that the aforeſaid <hi>Hoogerbeets, Grotius,</hi> and other Deputies comming to Vtrecht, to the intent aforeſaid, ſecretly and in priuate aſſemblies, aduiſed with ſome of the States of Vtrecht, and the Secretary <hi>Ledenberch,</hi> made propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching preſent reſiſtance, and how to moue the new companies thereunto, as alſo to procure the ordinary ſouldiers, by vertue of the letter aforeſaid, not to be obedient to the commandements of his Excellencie, and the Committies for the Generall States, and to ſecond them by the Artillerie men of the towne; to appoint places for the ſaid new
<pb facs="tcp:13795:18"/>
ſouldiers to aſſemble in; to haue diuers peeces of ordinance ready, and that <hi>Monſieur Modesberghen</hi> and <hi>Ledenberch</hi> had told them, that if they could finde a meanes to keep the ſouldiers that were then in ordinarie pay of Holland, from ſtirring, that they had taken ſuch order among their new ſouldiers, that they would eaſily obtaine their wills: and that alſo the ſaid <hi>Hoogerbeets</hi> with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, the day before the diſcharging of the aforeſaid new companies of ſouldiers, had deliuered their letters to the aforeſaid ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſouldiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="article">
               <head>32</head>
               <p>That he had reuealed the ſecrets of the Land, and contrary to the acts of ſoueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of his owne authoritie, without the knowledge or conſent of any of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, refuſed and denied to accept of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine notable vnexpected alliance, which in the higheſt degree concerned the Common wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:13795:18"/>
               <head>33</head>
               <p>That he procured diuers Courts of Iuſtice (in the adminiſtration of their offices) by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wayes, and in ſeuerall matters, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the lawes, priuiledges, freedomes, and ſtatutes of the Land, to vſe vntrue dealing in the adminiſtration of iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="article">
               <head>34</head>
               <p>And that he, contrary to his oath, and by the inſtructions of ſome forraine Princes, Lords, and others, receiued diuers great ſummes of money, and preſents, without making any that had to doe therewith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewithall. All which his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, tending to the end not only to make the towne of Vtrecht a ſlaughter-houſe, but alſo to bring the ſtate of the Land, and the perſon of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> into vtter ſubuerſion, whereby, and by meanes of all other his machinations and conſpiracies, it is ſo fallen out, that States
<pb facs="tcp:13795:19"/>
againſt States, gouernment againſt gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and new contracts in and againſt the vnitie, and generall perturbations in the ſtate of the Land, as well ſpirituall as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, are riſen vp, the treaſure conſumed, and the Country compelled to an expence of many millions of crownes, generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts and diſſentions moued and brought in among the vnited Prouinces, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land, the vnion broken, the Country made vnfit and vnapt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it ſelfe, and brought into danger, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and ſuffer ſome ſcandalous wrong, or vtterly to be ouerthrowne and ſubuerted: which are matters of ſuch conſequence, that they are not to be ſuffered in any gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but rather ought to be puniſhed, for an example to all others.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Iudges aforeſaid, with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration of the counſell of the States gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, hauing well conſidered vpon and weighed all the articles aforeſaid, wherein they concerned, or in any wiſe might tend to the matter in queſtion; doing iuſtice, in
<pb facs="tcp:13795:19"/>
the names and behalfes of the Generall States of the vnited Prouinces, haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and by theſe preſents condemne the ſaid priſoner, to be brought to the Inner Court, to the place thereunto appointed, there to haue his head ſtricken off, and all his goods, lands, and reuenues to be confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. Giuen in the aſſembly of the Iudges aforeſaid in the <hi>Grauen-Hage,</hi> and executed the 13. of May 1619.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By order from the Iudges aforeſaid.</hi> Signed H. POTZ.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:20"/>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION made by the Generall States of the <hi>vnited Netherland Prouinces, for the holding of a generall Faſt, and day of Praier for the good ſucceſſe of the Synode, and peace and preſeruation of the</hi> LAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as it is ſo fallen out, by meanes of miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in certaine yeeres hitherto happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:13795:21"/>
not only in the Church, but alſo among the Commons of theſe Countries, and likewiſe in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique gouernment and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of iuſtice: that ſome am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious perſons, for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their particular deſignes and ambitions, to the great hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the reformed religion, and ſpeciall diſaduantage of the ſeruice of the Land, ſtirred vp, ſought to haue reuerſed and annihilated the true religion, and together at one time, wholly to haue ruinated and ſubuerted the ſtate of the Land, if the Nationall Synode had not beene ſummoned and called, by the aduice of moſt famous, learned, well experienced, honeſt, and godly perſons, ſtrangers, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb facs="tcp:13795:21"/>
of theſe Countries, to examine the differences in matters of religion, and the ſame to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and vtterly exterminate: as alſo, if we had not reſtored and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed the lawfull authoritie of gouernment and iuſtice, by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proceedings againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictors and violaters thereof<hi>:</hi> And for that they haue already proceeded ſo farre in the ſaid Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Synode, that the hardeſt and moſt important controuerſies and queſtions, with great vnitie and one generall conſent, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready determined and decided: And likewiſe that a lawfull Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſentence is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Iudges thereunto appointed by the Generall States
<pb facs="tcp:13795:22"/>
of the vnited Netherland Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, againſt thoſe that haue in ſuch ſort perturbed the ſtate of the Land, in ſuch manner that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of theſe vnited Netherlands both in ſpirituall and temporall matters, are apparant and likely to incline vnto a peaceable and quiet end: The Generall States of the ſaid vnited Netherland Prouinces haue thought it fit and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and likewiſe haue fully deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, to proclaime a common and generall Faſt, and day of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like praier, throughout all the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Netherland Prouinces, Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and Townes thereof, to be holden vpon Wedneſday the 17. of the month of Aprill, thereby and therein to praiſe and giue
<pb facs="tcp:13795:22"/>
thankes vnto the moſt mightie God for his grace and bleſsing, and with earneſt zeale and penitent hearts to pray vnto and call vpon him, that he would be pleaſed to continue his ſaid grace and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for the honour of his moſt holy name, and the planting and reſtoring of the true reformed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, together with the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and maintenance of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and lawfull authoritie of the ſaid vnited Netherlands, and the peace and tranquillitie of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the ſame, both in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and temporall proceedings. That ſo, with a good harmonie and one conſent, God Almightie may truly be called vpon and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; the ſtate of the Land ſecured;
<pb facs="tcp:13795:23"/>
and more and more proſper in their trade and continuall traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke; and all the counſels, machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and conſpiracies of the enemies of this Land broken and preuented, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13795:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
